Yes. So today's דף daf is דף כ'. daf chaf. And there's
going to be some interesting discussions of astronomy. We'll get to that
in a bit. But first we pick up with the continuing discussion.
So to remind you, we're talking about the שלוחים shluchim going out
at the various ראשי חדשים, Roshei Chadashim, which is related to the
question of, you know, when about like which month needs שלוחים shluchim
in terms of can we assume the length of the month? You
know, some months maybe have a more fixed length. So they went
out for ראש חודש תשרי, Rosh Chodesh Tishrei, although the general principle,
and I'm saying this because we're going to revisit it, is that
אלול Elul was always twenty-nine days. Nevertheless, there's always the possibility, so
they go out again for ראש חודש תשרי. Rosh Chodesh Tishrei. Similarly,
we're talking about them going out here, the issue of do they
going out for ניסן, Nissan, and the whole question of is there
an אדר שני Adar Sheini and what is the exact length of
it? A similar type of a question of do we always know
the length of the אדר? Adar? So, and that's both a question
of when they add a leap month, which is אדר ראשון, Adar
Rishon, is that either always thirty days or always twenty-nine days or
does it vary? And then the question is, is the length of
a, forget a leap
year, a normal אדר Adar that precedes ניסן, Nissan, whether it's a
normal one אדר Adar or whether it's an אדר שני, Adar Sheini,
is that a fixed size or not? So the גמרא Gemara yesterday
said right, had different opinions about that.
So, and we stopped and the last line was, you know, maybe
we'll pick up with that. י"ט עמוד ב', yud tet amud bet,
five lines from the bottom. We'll just read this.
Okay, now I'm going even further. Okay, ודרשם דחמא בר חסא היי
רבי סימאי. v'darsham deChama bar Chisa hei rabbi simai. So
do ten lines from the bottom. We'll do this quickly because we
did this yesterday. היי רבי סימאי משום חגי זכריה ומלאכי על שני
אדרים שאם רצו לעשותם שניהם מלאים עושים שניהם חסרים עושים אחד מלא
ואחד חסר עושים וכך היו נוהגים בגולה. Hei Rabbi Simai mishum Chaggai
Zechariah uMalachi al shnei adarim sheim ratzu la'asotam shneihem mele'im osim, shneihem
chasereim osim, echad malei ve'echad chaser osim, vekach hayu nohagim bagola.
So you could do any size whether it's אדר ראשון Adar Rishon
or אדר שני, Adar Sheini, twenty-nine or thirty. ומשום רבינו אמרו, u'mishum
rabbeinu amru,
but in the name of the master רב, Rav, they said, ראוי
אחד מלא ואחד חסר. ra'uy echad malei ve'echad chaser. If it's two
אדרים, Adarim, the first one is מלא malei and the second one
is חסר, chaser, עד שיודע לך שהוא קבוע חודש
בזמנו. ad sheyivada lecha shehu kavu'a chodesh bizmano. בזמנו bizmano means that
the previous month was only twenty-nine. So it's always מלא malei and
חסר chaser unless you have definite knowledge that the אדר ראשון Adar
Rishon was only twenty-nine days. But you should assume thirty and twenty-nine.
Okay, שלחו ליה למר עוקבא, Shalchu lei leMar Ukva, they sent to
מר עוקבא, Mar Ukva, אדר הסמוך לניסן לעולם חסר. Adar hasamuch leNissan
le'olam chaser.
So regardless of whether it's a leap year or not, the אדר
Adar preceding ניסן, Nissan, so either אדר Adar or אדר שני, Adar
Sheini, is always going to be twenty-nine days. So מתיב רב נחמן,
Masif Rav Nachman, רב נחמן Rav Nachman challenged, על שני חדשים מחללים
את השבת על ניסן ועל תשרי. al shnei chodeshim mechallelim et haShabbat
al Nissan ve'al Tishrei.
We're going to see this משנה, Mishna, on two holidays the witnesses,
and not holidays, on two ראשי חדשים Roshei Chadashim for the sake
of testifying for two ראשי חדשים, Roshei Chadashim, the witnesses would violate
שבת Shabbat because they could do it because it's במועדו be'mo'ado in
order to do it at the right time. You can come and
carry and travel on שבת Shabbat in order to be able to
testify that you saw the moon the previous night. Which two months?
For ניסן Nissan and תשרי, Tishrei, because those are the ones that
are really critical because they affect the holidays. Now, אי אמרת, I
amarta, now again, ניסן Nissan of course follows אדר. Adar. So if
אדר Adar is always twenty-nine days, why do you need a witness
to violate שבת Shabbat to tell you when ראש חודש ניסן Rosh
Chodesh Nissan is? You know you're going to make ניסן Nissan on
the day on day thirty of אדר. Adar. If you have it
fixed, you don't care what the witnesses say. And this is introducing
this idea, as we're going to continue to see, that while we
make the new moon, the new month based on the testimony of
witnesses, we also have the latitude of ignoring the witnesses and just
doing what we want, which is by the way how the calendar
works nowadays when we don't have witnesses. So if you've decided אדר
Adar is always going to be twenty-nine days, who needs to violate
שבת Shabbat in order to testify about ניסן? Nissan? We know when
ניסן Nissan is going to be. We know it's going to be
day thirty. גמרא Gemara says no, אי אמרת בשלמא זימנין מלא וזימנין
חסר משום הכי מחללי. I amarta bishlama zimnin malei zimnin chaser mishum
hachi mechaleli. If you say sometimes אדר Adar is twenty-nine, sometimes thirty,
that's why you violate שבת Shabbat to testify about ניסן Nissan because
you want to know when to make ניסן. Nissan. אלא אי אמרת,
ella i amarta, top of כ' עמוד א', chaf amud aleph, אלא
אי אמרת לעולם חסר אמאי מחללי, ella i amarta le'olam chaser amai
mechaleli,
that אדר Adar is always twenty-nine days, why would you violate שבת
Shabbat if you know what day you're going to make ראש חודש
ניסן? Rosh Chodesh Nissan? You know it's going to be day thirty.
גמרא Gemara says no, משום דמצוה לקדש על הראיה, mishum d'mitzvah lekadesh
al har'iyah, that even though we know and we can do it
without witnesses, there's a מצוה mitzvah to use witnesses as the basis
of it, and for the sake of that מצוה mitzvah we will
violate שבת. Shabbat. Now of course as the גמרא Gemara is going
to ask, if that was your only issue, why are you limiting
yourself to ניסן Nissan and תשרי? Tishrei? ניסן Nissan and תשרי Tishrei
indicate it's not just because we want to do it based on
witnesses, but because the importance of getting these months right. So the
גמרא Gemara will get back to that. But at this stage we're
saying sure, we don't need them. We would have done it without
them. But they violate שבת Shabbat because we want to use them.
Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika de'amri,
some say, אמר רב נחמן אף אנן נמי תנינא, amar Rav Nachman
af anan nami tanyina, we taught similarly in our משנה Mishna that
אדר Adar is always twenty-nine. Now we're going to use it to
prove the opposite. davka support. על שני חודשים מחללין את השבת, Al
shnei chodashim mechallelin et haShabbat, על ניסן ועל תשרי. al Nissan ve'al
Tishrei.
Okay, so you violate שבת Shabbat to testify on ניסן Nissan and
תשרי. Tishrei. אי אמרת בשלמא Ei amart bishlama לעולם חסר, le'olam chaser,
if you said that אדר Adar is always חסר chaser and we
know which month is, we know which day is going to be
ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan without the witnesses, משום הכי מחללין,
mishum hachi mechallelin,
so even if day thirty of אדר, Adar, which we know is
going to be day one of ניסן, Nissan, falls out on שבת,
Shabbat, we would have the witnesses travel on שבת. Shabbat. Why? דמצוה
לקדש על פי הראיה, demitzvah lekadesh al pi hare'iyah,
because even if we know we're going to make this שבת Shabbat
ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, we want to use witnesses. That
makes sense. Okay, so why wouldn't it make sense the other way?
אלא אי אמרת זימנין מלא זימנין חסר, Ela ei amart zimnin malei
zimnin chaser, if, however, you say that אדר Adar could sometimes be
twenty-nine, sometimes thirty, says the גמרא, Gemara, אמאי מחללין, amai mechallelin,
why should you have to violate שבת? Shabbat? Why not? Don't you
want to get the witnesses to come on שבת Shabbat and make
it ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? No. נעברה להאידנא ונקדשיה למחר. Na'abreh l'idna
venikadsheh l'machar.
Let's just close our doors on שבת Shabbat on the day thirty
and have them come on Sunday and make day thirty-one ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh.
So you understand here's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. The גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming,
ignore this, we'll get back to this in a minute, but the
גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming the case is,
right here's your אדר, Adar, okay, twenty-nine, thirty, right, and this is
שבת, Shabbat, and this is Sunday, and this is like day thirty-one.
Well there's not going to be a day thirty-one but you get
the idea. So, if the גמרא Gemara assumes that this is how
this month fell out. So if we've already pre-decided
that אדר Adar is twenty-nine days and therefore this is going to
be ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, we've pre-decided that it has
to be because אדר Adar is only twenty-nine days. We know we're
going to make ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan on שבת. Shabbat.
So we're going to have to, and we want to use witnesses
to do it, we're going to accept the witnesses on שבת. Shabbat.
That makes sense that you violate שבת. Shabbat. But if you decide,
if אדר Adar can be twenty-nine or thirty, it's not fixed, why
violate שבת? Shabbat? Just close your doors, or close for business, have
the witnesses come on Sunday and we'll make this ראש חודש ניסן.
Rosh Chodesh Nissan. We won't have violated שבת Shabbat and we'll have
used witnesses. Okay, and of course maybe the witnesses will say we
saw it two days ago, but then it'll be too late, you
didn't accept them today. So okay, it's too late. Okay, so it's
a funny question because the answer could be, that's not being מקדש
על פי הראיה miekadesh al pi hare'iyah if their testimony isn't confirming
this as the day. But anyway, that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. If
you have some latitude, just close your doors here. Why do you
have to violate שבת? Shabbat? So let's see what the גמרא'ס Gemara's
answer is. אי דאקלה יום שלשים בשבת הכי נמי, Ei d'ikla yom
shloshim beShabbat hachi nami, if day thirty like I just drew fell
on שבת, Shabbat, you've got a good point. Maybe we would just
close our doors and do it on day thirty-one. הכא במאי עסקינן
דאקלה יום שלשים ואחד בשבת. Hacha bemai askinan d'ikla yom shloshim v'echad
beShabbat. We're talking about this wasn't the case. The case was that
this was Friday. So we're going to have to, the case
was that it was thirty,
no Friday was the thirty.
Friday, yeah right, thirty, thirty-one. This was the case. No, thirty became
Friday. So we're going to have to accept witnesses on שבת Shabbat
to make שבת Shabbat day one. And we do it על פי
הראיה. al pi hare'iyah. So that's the case. Our flexibility doesn't help
us. There were no witnesses here. So we're going to have to
make it day thirty-one into ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and that's a
שבת Shabbat and we'll have to accept witnesses on שבת. Shabbat. Okay.
All right. So that's the end of that discussion whether אדר Adar
is always twenty-nine days or whether it's flexible. מתיב רב כהנא, Mativ
Rav Kahana, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana went on to challenge this
issue about whether אדר Adar is always fixed as twenty-nine days. Now
remember our answer, we tried to prove it wasn't fixed from the
fact that the witnesses could violate שבת Shabbat to testify. And the
answer was no, it might still be fixed, but we might want
to do it in order to do it based on the witnesses
even if we already knew which day was ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
Let's see if that stands up. מתיב רב כהנא, Mativ Rav Kahana,
so רב כהנא Rav Kahana asked, כשהמקדש קיים מחללין אף אכולהו מפני
תקנת הקרבן. Keshehamikdash kayam mechallelin af akulahu mipnei takanat hakorban.
When there was the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, this is the end
of the משנה Mishnah we're going to see, then they would violate
שבת Shabbat to testify for any ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh because you
want to make sure you're bringing the right קרבן korban on the
right day. Okay. So we see what? You see that the question
of do you violate שבת Shabbat is not the issue of to
be מצוה לקדש על פי הראיה. mitzvah lekadesh al pi hare'iyah. If
the reason you would violate שבת Shabbat is just because it's nice
to do it, we want to do it based on witnesses, then
you would always do it on every month. You see from the
משנה Mishnah that whether you violate שבת Shabbat is not based on
just an abstract desire to testify based on witnesses. It's based on
the concrete implications of whether something hinges on getting the day right.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. מדכולהו לאו משום דמצוה לקדש
על פי הראיה, Midekulahu lav mishum demitzvah lekadesh al pi hare'iyah, you
see the other months, the reason you would violate שבת Shabbat is
not for the sake of a מצוה mitzvah to do it based
on testimony. The only reason you would violate שבת Shabbat for a
particular month is because there's a practical implication, like bringing the קרבן
korban in the right time, not just for this abstract thing of
oh we want to do it based on witnesses. So if that's
true... ניסן Nisan *Nisan* and תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei* נמי להוי משום דמצוה
לקדש על פי הראיה *nami lehve mishum d'mitzvah lekadesh al pi ha-re'iyah*.
The reason you would violate for ניסן Nisan *Nisan* and תשרי Tishrei
*Tishrei* is not because oh we know the date but anyway we
want to do it based on witnesses. No. You see you would
only violate שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* if there is a practical benefit, if
there's something practical hanging in the balance. Doing it for the sake
of having witnesses because it makes it nice, if that were true
we would do it on every month. אי אמרת בשלמא *Ei amarta
bishlama* so you see there's gotta be something that hinges on it.
אי אמרת בשלמא זימנין מלא וזימנין חסר *Ei amarta bishlama zimnin malei
zimnin chaser* if you say אדר Adar *Adar* is sometimes 29, sometimes
30, משום הכי מחללין *mishum hachi michallelin* then you understand why you
would violate שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* for ניסן Nisan *Nisan*, because you want
to make sure you've got the date right, you've got the date
in sync with where the moon appears. So that's why you do
it. אלא אי אמרת *Ela ei amarta* but if we've decided אדר
Adar *Adar* is going to be 29 and we're going to make
day 30 ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh* regardless of the moon,
so אמאי מחללין *amai michallelin* why would you violate? So again we're
back to the question. The fact that you violate שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*
shows we do not have it predetermined. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer
that we do have it predetermined but we do it because we
want to use witnesses, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here says that can't
be true. If that's true we would do that for every month
and we don't do it for every month. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says תיובתא *tiyuvta* you're right, that's a contradiction. The fact that
you violate שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* shows that the date is not predetermined,
shows that the date is hanging in the balance, and therefore you
see that אדר Adar *Adar* can sometimes be 29, can sometimes be
30. Okay and that seems to be the conclusion of the גמרא
Gemara's *Gemara*, which is good because we would like to believe at
least that when they were doing it based on witnesses, it wasn't
all prefixed. When they were doing it based on witnesses generally it
was based on witnesses. What we're beginning to see is some possibility
not that way, that certain aspects of it might have been predetermined
regardless of the witnesses. But anyway the conclusion at this stage is
that אדר Adar *Adar* was not fixed, it would be based on
whether the witnesses would show up or not. Okay or when the
witnesses would show up. כי אתא עולא *Ki ata Ulla* now when
עולא *Ulla* came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, אמר *amar*
he said the following: עברוהו לאלול *Ibruhu l'Elul* he said we actually
made אלול Elul *Elul* 30 days. We had taught yesterday, so we're
now moving on from אדר *Adar*. We've decided אדר *Adar* isn't necessarily
29, can sometimes be 30. By the way notice the parallel, right?
We had said מימות עזרא ואילך לא מצינו אלול Elul's מעובר *miyemot
Ezra va'eilach lo matzinu Elul me'ubar* which basically meant אלול Elul *Elul*'s
always 29 days. We've also been saying אדר *Adar* before ניסן Nisan
*Nisan* is always 29 days. So the starting point is that the
months before the months which determine the חגים *chagim* are always 29
days. So that's good. You have a fixed sense of the previous
month, it gives you confidence when תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei* will begin and
it gives you confidence when ניסן Nisan *Nisan* will begin. But right
now we've undermined אדר *Adar*. We've said actually it's not true, אדר
*Adar* could sometimes be 30 days. So we don't have total confidence
when ניסן Nisan *Nisan* begins. Now we had said that אלול Elul
*Elul*'s always 29 days, now we're going to go back and undermine
that a little bit. And עולא *Ulla*'s going to say yes it's
very nice that you said that אלול Elul *Elul* was always 29
days, I gotta tell you and I just came from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* and they made אלול Elul *Elul* 30 days.
Okay so that confidence that we have that אלול Elul, *Elul* is
always 29, אדר *Adar* is always 29, so you know when ניסן
Nissan *Nisan* begins, you know when תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei* begins has been
undermined. אדר *Adar* might not be 29, אלול Elul *Elul* that we've
said is always 29, עולא *Ulla* now comes and says there was
a year just now that they made אלול Elul *Elul* 30 days.
So כי אתא עולא *Ki ata Ulla* when עולא *Ulla* came from
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael* אמר *amar* he said: עברוהו לאלול
*Ibruhu l'Elul* they made אלול *Elul* 30 days. אמר עולא *Amar Ulla*
now עולא *Ulla* said: ידעי חבריין בבבל מאי טיבותא עבדינן בהדייהו *yadai
chavrain b'Bavel mai tivuta avdinan b'hadaihu* our Babylonian colleagues should know what
you know how what good we did for them, that we made
אלול *Elul* 30 days in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* and
how nice we were to them. Okay, so we're going to see
in a minute A, why was it nice and B, why was
it דוקא *davka* nice for them. Okay, but that's what עולא *Ulla*'s
saying. You know, you guys should know you should
acknowledge how nice we were in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*
that we made אלול *Elul* 30 days for you. So what's the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* going to say: מאי טיבותא *mai tivuta* okay what
what type of a favor is this? Now you could just be
saying like why is it a big deal, but תוספות Tosafot's *Tosafot*
actually gives a little bit more of a of a of a
like a thorn a punch to this question. If you look at
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*, מאי טיבותא *mai tivuta*, תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* says שמעברין
אלול דמוטב שלא יעברו כדי שלא יתראו ימים מספק *she-me'abrin Elul d'mutav
she-lo ya'avru kedei she-lo yitra'ei yamim misafek* תוספות *Tosafot* says what benefit
are you doing me? Oh we did it very nice we made
אלול *Elul* 30 days, it fixed some things. So the question is
like you know what? Don't do me any favors, just make אלול
*Elul* 29 days all the time and then I'll know when תשרי
Tishrei, *Tishrei* is, right? And then I won't have to have two
days of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah* and two days of
סוכות *Sukkot* and two days of שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeret*. I don't
need your favors. Let's just say אלול *Elul*'s 29 days period no
question. רבינו הקדוש עשה שני יומי
*Rabbeinu HaKadosh assei
shnei yomim* right right so that's what תוספות *Tosafot* is saying, it's
like it's a real question like whatever benefit I got you're about
to tell me that I got from you making אלול *Elul* 30
days, I'm not so clear it's such a benefit. I'd rather just
keep אלול *Elul* 29 days. So let's anyway see what the answer
is. מאי טיבותא *mai tivuta* what was the benefit? עולא אמר משום
ירקא *Ulla amar mishum yarka* so עולא *Ulla* who's the one who
came and said that there was this great thing they did and
it was a benefit, says it was because of vegetables. רב אחא
בר חנינא אמר משום מתיא *Rav Acha bar Chanina amar mishum metaya*
for dead bodies. What does this mean? We're going to see two
different scenarios. One is adjusting the calendar when שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* were if שבת *Shabbos* and יום
כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* were to fall out back to back.
Now in our calendar that never happens, right? שבת *Shabbos*, meaning יום
כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* is never on a Friday or a
Sunday. What would happen if it were to fall out back to
back? It would be two days you could not bury anybody, because
you don't bury anybody on שבת *Shabbos* even through having non-Jews do
it, and you don't bury dead bodies on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur*. So especially in hot climates and no refrigeration, two days
that you can't bury a body is a pretty serious problem. So
therefore that's מתיא *metaya*, we don't want it to be two days
of complete no burial of bodies. What's משום ירקא *mishum yarka*? משום
ירקא *mishum yarka* is a different issue. It's not שבת *Shabbos* and
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, it's שבת *Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yontif* back to back. What's the issue there? Well, you want fresh
vegetables for שבת *Shabbos* and you want your fresh vegetables for יום
טוב Yom Tov. *Yontif*. You don't have a refrigerator, so if שבת
*Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom Tov *Yontif* are never back to back,
you can always go to the garden and pick fresh vegetables the
day before. But if they're back to back and you picked fresh
vegetables on Friday, then comes Sunday יום טוב Yom Tov *Yontif* and
your vegetables are already wilted. So that's so one is a reason
to separate יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and שבת *Shabbos* so you don't
have two days you can't bury dead bodies, and the other's a
reason to separate יום טוב *Yontif* and שבת *Shabbos* so you don't
have two days in which so you have days in which you
could pick fresh food right before שבת *Shabbos* or right before יום
טוב *Yontif*. Yes.
Your second consideration was never brought up in all that discussion of
ערב פסח *Erev Pesach* on שבת *Shabbos*.
Right. So that obviously is not one because that doesn't factor into
our calendar as all of us know who have these multiple three-day
יום טובים *Yontifs*, that does not seem to be the issue that
dominates. It's the מתיא *metaya* is the issue. Let's take a look.
מאי בינייהו *Mai beinayhu*? What would be a difference between those considerations?
איכא בינייהו יום הכיפורים שחל להיות אחר השבת *Ika beinayhu Yom HaKippurim
shechal lihyot achar HaShabbos*. So here's how it's going to play out.
One concern addresses the issue of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* following שבת
*Shabbos* and said that we would adjust the calendar to make sure
that יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* doesn't fall out right after שבת *Shabbos*.
מאן דאמר משום מתיא *Man d'amar mishum metaya*, if your concern is
dead bodies, מעברין *maavrin*, then we would adjust the calendar to prevent
that from happening. ומאן דאמר משום ירקייא *U'man d'amar mishum yarkaya*, if
it's because of vegetables, so vegetables is not an issue on יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*. You're not eating on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. לאימת
קא בעי להו *Le'eimat ka ba'ei lehu*, when are you going to
need your fresh vegetables? לאורתא *L'orta*, after יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. לאורתא
טרח ומייתי *L'orta tarach u'maity*, so after יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, מוצאי
יום כיפור *Motzei Yom Kippur*, go pick your fresh vegetables. Now you
could by the way have said that fresh vegetables is an issue
of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* leading into שבת *Shabbos* because you want
your fresh vegetables on שבת *Shabbos*. But okay, that would be an
example where it would only be the concern of dead bodies and
not the concern of vegetables. And therefore we would adjust it according
to one, we wouldn't adjust it according to the other. ולמאן דאמר
משום ירקייא לעברין משום מתיא *U'le'man d'amar mishum yarkaya le'avrin mishum metaya*?
Gemara says look, this reason of dead bodies is a pretty serious
reason. So if you say your concern is vegetables, shouldn't you also
concede to the concern of dead bodies? So the Gemara says okay,
you're right. Everybody agrees to the concern of dead bodies. So nobody
will ever accept יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and שבת *Shabbos* back to
back. The whole debate is whether you also are concerned about this
vegetable issue. The dead body issue everybody is concerned about and that's
our calendar. יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and שבת *Shabbos* are never back
to back. What's at stake is is this vegetable thing a serious
concern? So the Gemara says אלא *ela*, so אלא איכא בינייהו יום
טוב הסמוך לשבת בין מלפניה בין מאחריה *ela ika beinayhu Yom Tov
hasamuch l'Shabbos bein milfaneha bein me'achareha*. יום טוב *Yontif* and שבת *Shabbos*
back to back, which as we know happens all the time. מאן
דאמר משום ירקייא *Man d'amar mishum yarkaya*, the one that's also concerned
about vegetables, מעברין *maavrin*, you would make a, you would add a
day in the of אלול *Elul* or whatever, a day of the
previous month in order to separate them, not have יום טוב *Yontif*
and שבת *Shabbos* back to back. ומאן דאמר משום מתיא *U'man d'amar
mishum metaya*, but if your only concern is dead bodies, אפשר בעממי
*efshar b'amamei*, so you can have non-Jews bury dead bodies on the
first day of יום טוב *Yontif*. Not on שבת *Shabbos*, but the
first day of יום טוב *Yontif*. So therefore יום טוב *Yontif* and
שבת *Shabbos* back to back is not a problem because on one
of those days you can get the body buried. You will not
go two days without burying the body. Okay, so the Gemara says
what's really the debate is do you believe in this vegetable concern?
Will you allow שבת *Shabbos* and יום טוב *Yontif* to be back
to back? So the Gemara says ולמאן דאמר משום מתיא לעברין משום
ירקייא *U'le'man d'amar mishum metaya le'avrin mishum yarkaya*, if you're only focusing
on the dead
body, why are you not concerned about the fresh vegetables? So I
mean obviously the answer could be like okay it's not such a
big deal, but anyway let's see what the Gemara says. אפשר בחמימי
*Efshar b'chamimei*, because what you could do is you could heat up
the vegetables or keep them in warm water and that'll keep them
relatively fresh. So the fact that they're not 100 percent fresh or
whatever it's not going to make me all of a sudden adjust
the calendar just for that. And as we know, we do have
שבת *Shabbos* and יום טוב *Yontif* back to back. So now, now
we've established what's the issue. Why they would adjust the calendar to
prevent שבת *Shabbos* and יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*, or maybe even שבת
*Shabbos* and יום טוב *Yontif* from being back to back. So now
we have to get to why should we in בבל Bavel. *Bavel*
feel a particular sense of gratitude? I mean okay, why is it,
is this true for anybody? Why is it דווקא *davka* something we
in בבל Bavel *Bavel* should be grateful for? So the Gemara says
אי הכי מאי שנא לדידן *Ee hachi mai shna l'didan*? Why is
it special for us? אפילו לדידהו lididhu נמי *Afilu l'didhu nami*, even
for them in Israel... in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael this is an
equal benefit. גמרא Gemara says no, לדידן חבילא לן עלמא. lididun chavila
lanu alma. For us the world is very hot and humid and
therefore the concern of the you know the sort of decomposing dead
bodies or the wilting of the vegetables are a heightened concern in
בבל. Bavel, לדידהו for them in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael לא חבילו
עלמא lo chavilu alma they have nice more you know breezes and
it's less humid and they've got the beautiful Mediterranean weather. So for
them dead bodies and decomposing bodies and wilting vegetables are not as
big of an issue. So we in בבל Bavel should feel particularly
grateful that they've adjusted the calendar to prevent this from happening. You
know but going back to תוספות's point it's like okay but maybe
I still would rather just know when ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is
going to be and only have one יום טוב. So the גמרא
Gemara never really addresses that but here is this point. On the
one hand you have the on the one side you have the
confidence of when תשרי Tishrei, is going to be or the earlier
discussion about אדר the confidence of when ניסן is going to be.
And the other possibility is honestly being responsive to the witnesses or
adjusting the calendar for other types of for other types of realities.
So on the one hand we got to say אדר could be
twenty-nine or thirty days based on the witnesses. Here we're saying אלול
although we've always said אלול's always twenty-nine days we're saying no once
it was thirty and we actually will adjust אלול maybe even regardless
of witnesses in order to avoid these other types of issues about
יום כיפור and שבת being back to back. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now איני eini is this really true that we can intentionally adjust
the calendar and ignore the witnesses? Now we're getting to the heart
of it right? This is a theme we've been talking about until
now. If אדר is always twenty-nine days we're going to ignore the
witnesses or the opposite here. If we're going to make אלול thirty
days maybe we're doing it intentionally to manipulate the calendar. So is
this really true that you can manipulate the calendar in disregard of
the witnesses? והא v'ha is this really true? Where am I? והא
תני רבה בר שמואל v'ha tani Rabba bar Shmuel did רבה בר
שמואל Rabba bar Shmuel teach יכול כשם שמעברין את השנה לצורך כך
מעברין את החודש לצורך? yachol k'shem she'mabrin et hashana l'tzorech kach mabrin
et hachodesh l'tzorech?
Perhaps the same way we can adjust the year for a need
we can just add an extra month in order to get the
seasons you know
sync. Maybe we can also adjust a month for a need add
an extra day to a month regardless of the witnesses for these
types of concerns we've just mentioned. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar the verse
teaches החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים. hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim.
This is for you a ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh כזה ראה וקדש
kazeh r'eh v'kadesh like this you should see and you should sanctify.
So see
sanctify based on what the witnesses say on what the moon is
that they saw and not based on your own external concerns of
adjusting the calendar for other reasons. So you see so you see
you have to be based on testimony. How could we say we
adjusted it for these various issues? So אמר רבא amar Rava so
says רבא Rava לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult כאן לעברו
כאן לקדשו. kan l'abro kan l'kadsho. How are we adjusting the calendar?
Are we adjusting the calendar by the witnesses said it should have
been that it should have been day thirty was ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh and we ignored them and we made it day thirty-one? That's
ignoring them לעברו. l'abro. They wanted to make a twenty-nine day month
and we made it into a thirty day month. There's another way
of ignoring them which is לקדשו. l'kadsho. The witnesses did not come
today it would have been a thirty-day month and we sanctified it
early we made it a twenty-nine day month. So let me ask
you which one is a more of a disregarding of the witnesses?
To they came on day thirty and we ignored them and made
it on day thirty-one? That's ignoring them לעברו. l'abro. Or they didn't
come at all on day thirty and we sanctified day thirty without
witnesses? That's ignoring them לקדשו. l'kadsho.
Again קידוש kiddush means to make it early to make it a
twenty-nine day month the previous one לעברו l'abro makes it a full
month. Which one do you think is a more in defiance or
in ignoring of the witnesses?
The first one say you actually had witnesses then they were you
they were right in front of you.
So you could say in the first one you disregarded them they
testified and you ignored them and you didn't make it ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh and you waited till the next day. Now argue me
the other way.
Well in the first you're ignoring the idea of witnesses completely.
Exactly. In in the case where they came they testified and after
you accepted their testimony you sanctified you just sanctified a day late
but at least you did the right thing you accepted their testimony
and you sanctified. Whereas in the other case they didn't show up
and you sanctified without witnesses. So we're going to see the גמרא's
Gemara going to sort of argue both ways but it's going to
say maybe we have more latitude in one of those scenarios rather
than the other. Okay and the first way it's going to say
is if you get the witnesses today on day thirty and then
you sanctify day thirty-one that's לעברו l'abro that's not as bad. At
least you did כזה ראה וקדש. kazeh r'eh v'kadesh. You saw the
moon you had testimony of the moon and you sanctified. Maybe a
little a little delayed but you still did the right procedure. Okay
and that would be better. Okay so let's take a look. And
as we saw before about אלול the חידוש chiddush was that they
added the day, they made אלול 30 days, so they adjusted it
by delaying, okay, and that's one thing. כאן לעברו, kan la'avro, in
one case it's a delaying, כאן לקדשו kan lekadsho in the other,
it's doing it early. והכי קאמר, ve-hachi ka'amar, and that doing it
early is the problem. יכול כשם שמעברין את השנה ואת החודש לצורך,
yakhol keshem she-me'abrin et ha-shanah ve-et ha-chodesh le-tzorech,
perhaps the same way we add an extra month to the year
and we add an extra day to the month for a need,
that's okay to do it late, כך נקדשין את החודש לצורך, kach
nekadshin et ha-chodesh le-tzorech,
maybe the same way we could we could do the month early
for a need, make it a 29-day month, a previous month? תלמוד
לומר החודש הזה לכם כזה ראה וקדש. talmud lomar ha-chodesh ha-zeh lachem
kaze re'eh ve-kadesh.
No,
first you have to see then you have to sanctify. So you
could do it a day late, you could postpone like we did
before, we made a 30-day אלול, but you can't do it a
day early. Okay, so that's what we're saying right now. We're not
done. וכי הא דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, ve-chi ha de-amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, like what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi says, מאיימין על העדים על החודש שנראה בזמנו לעברו. me'aymin al
ha-edim al ha-chodesh she-nir'ah bi-zmano le-avro. You can put the fear of
God, you can you know make the עדים edim scare the עדים
edim if they saw the moon in its time. בזמנו bi-zmano means
that the previous month was a 29-day month. So you can scare
them to say לעברו, le-avro, don't show, shut up, don't give your
testimony, in order to allow us to make it the previous month
a full month, okay? So you can ignore the witnesses or silence
the witnesses in order to add a day to the month, okay?
ואין מאיימין על העדים על החודש שלא נראה בזמנו לקדשו. ve-ein me'aymin
al ha-edim al ha-chodesh she-lo nir'ah bi-zmano le-kadsho. But you don't put
scare them to testify that they saw the moon a day before
they did in order to make it early. Now that clearly would
be the most intolerable, that we would actually suborn perjury, right? We
would actually get them it's one thing to say no witnesses showed
up we're making it ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. anyway. It's another thing
to get them to testify that they saw it today, a day
early when they didn't actually see it, to get them to testify
falsely. But you do see this difference. We will not do it
a day early, we will do it, we will shut them up
and do it a day late. But we won't force them to
testify a day early falsely. And by in parallel what we're saying
is we also won't even just do it without them. We won't
do it early, we will do it late. Now we're not done,
but that's where we are at this stage, yes.
These witnesses, the court knows what to expect from the witness in
terms of what it when to suspect exactly, right?
So how could
they even consider this second possibility because they
have to know.
Right, but that's right, but that's the thing. They have external reasons
they want to adjust the calendar, like they don't want יום כיפור
and שבת to be back-to-back. So we're disregarding astronomy, disregarding witnesses, we're
going to make it we're going to make we're going to sanctify
you know today as you know we'll make the previous month 29
days. Now it's one thing to not bother with witnesses, it's another
thing to actually get them to testify falsely. So I think we
can all agree we're not going to get them to testify falsely.
But the גמרא Gemara is actually going one step further and saying
and we won't even do it early regardless. We want to first
get testimony and then do it. Okay, but we're not done. הגמרא
ha-Gemara says איני והא שלח ליה רב יהודה נשיאה לרבי אמי. eini
ve-ha shelach leh Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah le-Rabbi Ami. רב יהודה נשיאה Rav
Yehuda Nesi'ah now often רב יהודה נשיאה Rav Yehuda Nesi'ah is understood
is the grandson of רב יהודה הנשיא, Rav Yehuda ha-Nasi, but תוספות
says this is the actually a much later רב יהודה נשיאה Rav
Yehuda Nesi'ah because he was a contemporary of רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami.
Anyway, he sent to רבי אמי, Rabbi Ami, הוי יודעין, hevei yode'in,
be aware שכל ימיו של רבי יוחנן, she-kol yamav shel Rabbi Yochanan,
all of the life of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, היה מלמדנו, hayah
melamdenu, he would always teach us the following thing. מאיימין על העדים
על החודש שלא נראה בזמנו לקדשו. me'aymin al ha-edim al ha-chodesh she-lo
nir'ah bi-zmano le-kadsho. The exact opposite of what we said. We actually
would scare the witnesses to give testimony a day early, something that
they had not seen, to testify they had seen it, in order
that we to do it a day early. אף על פי שלא
ראו, af al pi she-lo ra'u, even though in case you had
any doubts what he's saying, here we are, even though they did
not see it, יאמרו ראינו, yomru ra'inu, we would get them to
say we saw it. So we would actually not only be prepared
to do the
calendar earlier than what's appropriate, but even scaring the witnesses to say
it. אמר אביי, amar Abaye,
so says אביי, Abaye, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא
בניסן ובתשרי הא בשאר ירחי. ha be-Nisan u-ve-Tishrei ha bi-shear yarchei. The
difference is ניסן and תשרי Tishrei versus the other months. Why? ניסן
and תשרי determine the holidays. So ניסן and תשרי are the months
where we have the greatest need to adjust the calendar, right? That's
what we've been talking about before. The great need to adjust the
calendar relates to יום טוב. So when we really need to adjust
the calendar like ניסן and תשרי, we're going to do it regardless
of witnesses. We'll do it late, we'll do it early, not only
will we do it early, maybe we'll even get them to testify
falsely. Now that's the hardest pill to swallow. It's one thing to
say you do it early, it's another thing to say you get
them to do it falsely. Okay, but that's what it's saying. ניסן
and תשרי, that we're going to adjust the calendar at will. Other
months then we'll only do it late, we won't do it early,
and then we're certainly not going to get the witnesses to lie.
Okay, that's his answer. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now רבא Rava has
a different answer. הא דתני רבה בר שמואל, ha de-tani Rabbah bar
Shmuel, that's Statement of רבא בר שמואל Rava bar Shmuel that's been
giving us a headache, that says that we don't, you know, we
have to always base ourselves on witnesses, we don't adjust the months,
that's אחרים היא, Acherim hi, that's not a consensus, that's a דעת
יחיד, da'at yachid, that's others, others meaning רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. דתניא,
Detanya, we quote in a ברייתא, braita, אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, others
meaning רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says, אין בין עצרת לעצרת ein bein
Atzeret l'Atzeret ואין בין ראש השנה לראש השנה, v'ein bein Rosh Hashanah
l'Rosh Hashanah, there is no gap between, you know, שבועות Shavuot and
שבועות, Shavuot, or ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, and ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah
meaning any two dates on the Hebrew calendar from one year to
the next, אלא ארבעה ימים בלבד, ela arba'ah yamim bilvad, only four
days, ואם הייתה שנה מעוברת חמישה, v'im hayta shana m'uberet chamisha, and
in the leap year five. Why?
Because how, how long is the Hebrew year? How many days is
the Hebrew year?
354 normally, which is, 350 is fifty weeks with four days remaining.
So any date that's ראש השנה one year, the next year is
four days later. Now, if a leap year is always twenty-nine days,
so you take out twenty-eight and that gives you one extra day.
So in a leap year, it makes a five-day shift, and in
a non-leap year a four-day shift. Now if I told you that,
that in any year from one date to the next in the
next calendar it's always going to be exactly a four-day shift, you
would say that sounds to me like you have a pre-fixed calendar
not based on witnesses, right? It's all predetermined. The גמרא Gemara's here
is reading it in the opposite. The גמרא Gemara's here is reading
it like no, if we keep our mess, our like troublesome hands
out of the calendar and just let astronomy determine, then that's the
natural astronomical reality is a four-day shift. That's what will happen if
we don't fiddle with it. So if you can confidently say it'll
only be a four-day shift if you're always really looking at the
month and you're not fiddling and adjusting. But if you're fiddling and
adjusting for יום כיפור and שבת and יום טוב and who knows
what, maybe it'll be five, maybe it'll be six, maybe it'll be
three. Four days is what you can say if you always base
yourself on astronomy. Now the problem with that is, I should say,
it's one thing to base yourself on astronomy, it's another the fact
that the astronomy is dependent on what? It's not just you look
at your charts and you know, right? It's dependent on people coming
in and testifying.
So it could very well be that that's exactly
twelve lunar months, but it doesn't mean the witnesses will necessarily have
seen it, it might have been a cloudy day, right? So on
the, one of the, on one of the last days, it might
be cloudy they won't see it, they'll come a day late. So
it's not exactly clear to me how we can confidently say this
will always happen if it's based on astronomical reality as witnessed by
real people based on weather conditions. Now you could say it'll always
be adjusted because if in one month they didn't see it and
they should have saw it on day thirty and it was cloudy
and they didn't, so that month wound up having been a thirty-day
month instead of a twenty-nine, by the next month it'll adjust back,
right? Because, because you can't keep on adding days because, you know,
the months keep on adjusting back. Over time it will adjust, but
it doesn't mean every year it will have adjusted soon enough. So
it is a little funny that the גמרא Gemara. asserts that this
means that this is always based on no fiddling, exactly what the
witnesses say, but that's what the גמרא Gemara says. You're right, forget
all of our qualifications before. We were making distinctions, we'll do it
late, we won't do it early, we won't have them lie, we'll
just have them shut up, you know, maybe it depends if it's
ניסן and תשרי or something else. The גמרא Gemara, says forget that.
We can, we're going to adjust it at will and maybe we'll
get them to lie if we need them to lie, we'll do
whatever we want. That statement that we don't fiddle with it and
we don't adjust it, that's the position of אחרים, Acherim, that's the
position of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that says we don't fiddle with
it. But that's not our position. Our position is we adjust it
as we need to. Yes.
Well there's also the possibility of clouds.
Right. Well that's what I meant, weather conditions and clouds.
And then there's another one which is the average length of the
months that we see
is twenty-nine and roughly twenty-nine and a half days, but the individual
months can be a little shorter, a little longer because of the
eccentricities in the orbit.
Okay, so you've lost me already, but yes. So that's the point,
that to say that this idea is based on, you know, on
direct observation and not fiddling with it, you won't, it would not
have that degree of predictability. There are weather conditions, there are clouds,
there are other things and it will adjust over time, but not
necessarily on a year by year basis. Anyway, that's the גמרא's Gemara
answer. The גמרא's Gemara. answer at this stage is forget any qualifications,
we will adjust it at will. The idea that we don't adjust
it and it's all based on witnesses, that's the אחרים. Acherim. Okay.
רב דימי מנהרדעא Rav Dimi m'Nehardea מתני איפכא. matni ipcha. Now by
the way, now we're going to have, going back to this question
of will we have a preference or a, you know, a reservation
of doing one type of adjusting versus the other? He says the
opposite of what we were saying. מאיימין על העדים על החודש שלא
נראה בזמנו לקדשו, m'aimin al ha'edim al hachodesh shelo nira bizmano l'kadsho,
you actually will more get them to lie and do it a
day early than, because then at least you're doing it based on
testimony. Okay, false testimony, a little asterisk, but still based on testimony,
that we will do.
ואין מאיימין על העדים על החודש v'ein m'aimin al ha'edim al hachodesh
הא מחזי כשיקרא הא מחזי כשיקרא הא לא מחזי כשיקרא. Ha mechzi
k'shikra ha mechzi k'shikra ha lo mechzi k'shikra.
In one case it looks like a lie, in the other case
it doesn't look like a lie. So you've got to love the
irony. So here's the case. Nobody saw the moon today because it
really wasn't visible, but we have a need to adjust the calendar.
So we're going to get witnesses to lie and say they saw
it, and we're going to make today ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh, So
I go to you Charlie and I say, "Today was ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh witnesses came and saw the moon." You're not going to
say, "Oh that can't be, I looked outside and I didn't see
it", because you'll figure I wasn't looking closely, it was cloudy, you'll
figure there's a reason you didn't see it. You'll trust me when
I say witnesses said they saw it and we made it ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh, even though they didn't see it and we got
them to lie. But here's the other scenario. Witnesses saw it today
and I'm going to come and say, "Yeah but today isn't ראש
חודש, Rosh Chodesh, tomorrow is ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, nobody saw it
and nobody came and testified." And you Charlie, you're going to say,
"What are you talking about? Me and my ten friends were out,
it was as clear as day, we all saw it. How could
it be that you're saying today isn't ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, nobody
came and testified?" Right? So that's מחזי כשיקרא. Mechzi k'shikra.
So they're not detaining them. What? They're not detaining them.
So basically we will be prepared to do it early and even
force them to lie to do it early because we won't get
caught in our lie. But we won't silence them and do it
late because then it'll be obvious that we're actually manipulating it. So
you've got to love the irony. Here's the irony. We would rather
engage in a lie which doesn't look like a lie. We would
rather get them to lie if it doesn't look like we're lying
than just get them quiet, right, if that looks like a lie.
So we're more concerned with the appearances of a lie than the
actual fact of getting them to testify falsely. Is that clear what's
happening here? All right anyway, so it reminds me of a תשובה
Teshuvah of רב יחזקאל אברמסקי Rav Yechezkel Abramsky about the whole question
of gelatin. You know about gelatin which comes from like the bones
of pigs and so on and does it get processed enough so
that it's not really considered you know אסור Assur anymore? It's all
dried out bones etc. So he basically writes this תשובה Teshuvah and
he says technically it's מותר, Muttar, it's totally מותר Muttar gelatin. He
says, but he says, we can't say it's מותר. Muttar. Why can't
we say it's מותר? Muttar? He says because the reform rabbis who
basically think that oh you know you can make הלכה Halakha say
whatever you want it to say and you can totally manipulate it,
so they'll say, "Look you know we're right. The rabbis took pig
and they said it was מותר, Muttar, they said gelatin is מותר,
Muttar, you see you can just do whatever you want with הלכה."
Halakha. So in order not to feed into the reform rabbis, you
know, we're going to have to say it's אסור. Assur. So when
I teach this I say you notice the irony. In order so
it doesn't look like we can manipulate הלכה Halakha as we want,
we're going to manipulate הלכה Halakha and say that it's אסור Assur
so it doesn't look like we can manipulate הלכה. Halakha. So that's
what you get in this גמרא. Gemara, So it's better to get
them to lie so it won't look like we're lying. Anyway, that's
his position. His position is we're more prepared to manipulate the calendar
to do it early rather than manipulate the calendar to do it
late. Okay.
So that's now the end of that discussion for now. אלול can
sometimes... אדר can sometimes be 29 sometimes 30. אלול can even sometimes
be 30. We will manipulate the calendar not to have יום כיפור
and שבת back to back, maybe even not to have יום טוב
and שבת back to back although that's not the way we rule.
Okay we will manipulate the calendar. Are there limits to manipulating the
calendar? In the end we basically say no, we can manipulate it
at will. Maybe there's a preference of doing it late rather than
early
because then we're not sort of like disregarding witnesses or we're actually
doing the process of taking witnesses and so on, doing the right
order. Maybe there's a preference of doing early rather than late because
as long as we do it early it's not obvious that we're
lying. Of course what's even more shocking is not just that we're
choosing to do it early but that we're actually getting witnesses to
lie in order to play along to allow us to do it
early. So those are the various issues in terms of the fact
that we will adjust the calendar as we need to. Now we're
going to get to some straight astronomy discussion so get your astronomy
thinking caps on. All right let's take a look.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, says שמואל Shmuel who we know was a
big בקי Baki in astronomy.
יכילנא לתיקוני לכולה גולה. Yachilna l'situnei l'chulei gola. I could set up
the calendar for the entire exile. Presumably says exile A he lived
in exile but B since we're so dependent on the קידוש על
פי הראיה Kiddush al pi hare'iyah that gets done in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and we never exactly know what's happening and we always
have to do an extra day, says you know if I wanted
to I could just set up the entire calendar based on the
astronomy which as we know is what happened in the time of
הלל השני. Hillel Hasheni. Of course you're not going to do it
different for exile and for ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, we have to
have a shared calendar. But anyway he says I got this whole
astronomy thing figured out I could set up a whole calendar. אמר
ליה אבא אבוה דרבי שמלאי לשמואל. Amar lei Abba avuh d'Rabbi Simlai
l'Shmuel. to Shmuel, ידע מר האי מילתא דתניא בסוד העיבור? Yada mar
hai milta d'tanya b'sod ha'ibbur?
Do you know what is meant by this line that we teach
in the סוד העיבור, sod ha'ibbur, the secret
of the pregnancy of meaning
of the determination of the month? So there was basically like a
little book that they had, you know that had all of the
secret rules of how you make the of astronomy and it was
called the secret, okay, so do you know what this and anyway
whatever the things were they were said very cryptically. Apparently most of
it was like a תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be'al peh. So do
you know what this line means that we teach that's taught in
סוד העיבור, sod ha'ibbur, נולד קודם חצות או נולד אחר חצות? nolad
kodem chatzos o nolad achar chatzos? Do you know what the significance
of that
is? It matters whether the מולד molad that there's a big difference
if the מולד molad was before or after חצות. chatzos. Do you
know what the significance of that is? אמר ליה לא, Amar lei
lo, said
no. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said אה דהא לא ידע
מר, ah de'ha lo yada mar, if you don't know what that
line means so איכא מילי אחרינייתא דלא ידע מר ika milei achrineiyata
d'lo yada mar then there must be a lot of other things
you don't know. Don't be such a, oh, I can set up
the calendar. Yeah let me test you. What does this little line
here mean? Oh you don't know? There's got to be other things
you don't know either. All right. So now
כי סליק רב זירא שלח להו, ki salik Rav Zeira shelach lehu,
when רב זירא Rav Zeira went to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael he
sent back to the exile the following line. צריך שיהא לילה ויום
מן החודש. Tzarich she-yehai layla v'yom min hachodesh. Number one, the day
and night have to be from the month. Now what does that
mean? So you can already see there's a long רש"י, Rashi, a
long
תוספות, just to give you a sense of how complicated or obscure
the גמרא Gemara is that we're reading, it's very cryptic, the גמרא,
Gemara like you
know with this סוד העיבור, sod ha'ibbur, you do actually wonder what
did they feel that it was some like religious secret whether there
was a point about keeping it secret other than just being like
a difficult thing, but anyway but just to give you a sense
about how much is written on it, so the בעל המאור, Ba'al
HaMa'or, רב זרחיה הלוי, Rav Zerachyah HaLevi, twelfth century, okay, this is
his commentary on these few lines of גמרא Gemara. that we're about
to read. Okay, you see this?
That's what he wrote on these few lines of גמרא. Gemara, So
anyway, back to our גמרא, Gemara. and night and the day have
to be from the month. What does this mean? What רש"י Rashi
says it means is the following, as רש"י Rashi says it means
that let's say now the first of all the first thing you
have to know is the principle of what we're about to read
in the גמרא Gemara which is כ"ד שעי מכסי סיהרא. kaf-daled sha'ei
machsei sihara. סיהרא Sihara is the moon.
The moon is hidden for twenty-four hours. Okay, what happens is is
in the case of the old moon, okay, the moon basically moves
relative to the sun in a counterclockwise direction. It goes three hundred
sixty degrees over thirty days, twelve degrees a day, about a half
a degree an hour, okay, so it's moving back counterclockwise. This is
the old moon. It's a little bit in front of the sun,
so you see it, the sun is below the horizon, so you
see the moon at the beginning of the day, if you really
want to call it it's the very end of the night, right,
because it's before the sun rises, so it's the very end of
the night you see the old moon. Then you don't see it
because the sun comes up and obviously it's too close and you
can't see, and then it sets before the sun, so the only
time you see it is at the very end of the night,
okay.
Then it gets closer and closer to the sun, it's in line
with the sun, you can't see it at all, it's still can't
see it because it's not yet enough out of the plane of
the sun, and then the new moon is visible when it moves
enough out of the enough behind the sun, so now you don't
see it in the beginning of the day because it's traveling right
behind the sun and it's too bright and you can't see, then
the sun sets and you see it right at the beginning of
the night, right, once the sun sets it's nighttime you see it
right at the beginning of the night and then it sets and
you can't see it. So the old moon you see at the
very end of the night right before sunrise, and that's confusing, you
see it right before sunrise, and the new moon you see right
after sunset, okay.
Now from the time it gets too close to the sun till
it becomes far enough away till it becomes visible is twenty-four hours,
okay, so there's twenty-four hours where the moon is not actually visible.
Now actually רמב"ם Rambam actually writes it's closer to two days. The
reality is is that in general it's assumed this is again what
little I read about this, it needs to be nine degrees removed
to be visible, okay, nine degrees removed is eighteen hours, right, for
the half a degree per hour is eighteen hours, which means that
eighteen hours times two, right, within the first nine
degrees in this direction and nine degrees in that direction it's really
thirty-six hours it's not visible. But the גמרא Gemara says twenty-four, okay,
so that's basically principle number one. Now
to this line in the גמרא. The line says that Where was
the line? לילה ויומי החודש. Laila v'yomei hachodesh. So רש״י Rashi says,
I'm just going to give you רש״י Rashi's read of this, which
is an easy read, so like this. That if in on a
particular day, let's say on day 30, which as day 30 always
has the potential of being ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh. okay, here's day
30, it starts halakhically at the night, here's the day, you saw
the old moon, you know, as, you know, because the old moon
you see at the very end of the night. Okay, so you
saw, you saw the old moon on the night of day 30.
So I guess it would be here right before daybreak. You saw
the old moon. Okay, you saw the old moon on day 30.
So רש״י Rashi says לילה ויומי החודש Laila v'yomei hachodesh means if
you saw the old moon during the night, you cannot in the
day make the day say, oh, I saw the new moon and
make it ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh, So the answer is, of course
you can. There's at least 24 hours from the time you saw
the old moon till the time you're going to see the new
moon. Of course you can. So רש״י Rashi says this goes back
to our earlier discussion of how much we will manipulate the calendar,
you know, based on people's knowledge otherwise. And רש״י Rashi points out
if people saw the old moon, if the old moon was visible
on this day, even if you wanted to manipulate the calendar, you
know, and say we're going to call it ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh
you can't. It's way too obvious that today isn't ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh because people saw the moon the night before. And people know
that the new moon isn't going to come out for at least
another 24 hours. Okay, so that's where רש״י Rashi says that line
goes. Okay, so let's read that again.
If the witnesses saw the old moon...
no, they knew of the old moon, but they didn't have testimony
about it. Okay, so לילה ויומי החודש, Laila v'yomei hachodesh,
the night and the day are both connected for the month. If
you saw the moon, the old moon in the night, you're not
going to make the day and say you saw the new moon
and make it ראש חודש even if you wanted to manipulate the
calendar. That's what רש״י Rashi says. Now back to the line we
said before: וזו שאמר אבא בנו דרבי סימלאי מחשבין את תולדתה. v'zo
she'amar Abba bno d'Rabbi Simlai mchasvin et toldatah.
This statement of אבא, Abba, the father of רבי סימלאי Rabbi Simlai
about before חצות chatzot and after חצות. chatzot. Here's what it means:
מחשבין את תולדתה, mchasvin et toldatah, you figure out the מולד. molad.
The מולד molad is when the moon first moves off of the
parallel plane, starts moving out of the plane of the sun towards...
it's not yet visible, like we said, there needs to be, you
know, 9 degrees so that it's visible, but when it starts going
off of the zero degrees and astronomically it's not in the same
place, that's the מולד. molad. So you determine the מולד. molad. מולד
קודם חצות בידוע שנראה סמוך לשקיעת החמה לא נולד קודם חצות בידוע
שלא נראה סמוך לשקיעת החמה.
Molad kodem chatzot beyadua shenireh samuch l'shkiat hachamah lo nolad kodem chatzot
beyadua shelo nireh samuch
l'shkiat hachamah. Okay,
so if the מולד molad happens before חצות, chatzot, then you know
that it'll be visible before sunset. If the מולד molad happened after
חצות, chatzot, it won't be visible before sunset. למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai
nafka mina? Why do I care whether it'll be visible or not?
אמר רב אשי לאכחושי סהדי, Amar Rav Ashi l'achchushei sahadi, so that
you can contradict the witnesses. If the witnesses say something that is
not astronomically possible, you know they're lying and you know that you
can contradict them. That's why we had to know the astronomy, so
we could know whether we could believe what the witnesses were saying.
Now, what does this mean, נולד nolad before חצות chatzot or after
חצות? chatzot? Because again, the new moon, hold on, let me see
if I get this right...
yes, the new moon is going to be seen סמוך לשקיעת החמה,
samuch l'shkiat hachamah, right? That's what we said. Right? The new moon
travels behind the sun, it's going to be seen סמוך לשקיעת החמה.
samuch l'shkiat hachamah. So the assumption here is, not like we just
said that it takes 18 hours to be visible, the assumption of
the גמרא, which I can't defend, is that it will be visible
in six hours. Once it's six hours removed from the plane, it'll
be visible, the moon will be visible. So if the מולד, molad,
if they were exactly lined up here, right? If... yes, you're with
me? If they were exactly lined up here, that was the מולד,
molad, it started, you know, it exactly started moving, then six hours
later it'll be enough removed from the plane to be visible. So
if the מולד molad was קודם חצות, kodem chatzot, right at this
point it started moving off of the plane right before חצות, chatzot,
קודם חצות, kodem chatzot, then six hours later, right? It'll be visible
because six... assuming that six is... it only takes six hours to
be visible, then six hours later at sunset, now it's visible and
now you'll see it at sunset. But if it was נולד nolad
after חצות, chatzot,
right, and here's where it starts to become visible... I mean, here's
where it starts to move off the plane, so it becomes visible
six hours later, so six hours later it's already below the horizon.
You with me? Okay, so if it started moving off the plane
here before חצות, chatzot, then it'll be visible six hours later and
that'll be right after... right at sunset, right after sunset. If it
moved off the plane after חצות... chatzot... If it moves off the
plane after חצות, Chatzos, then six hours later it'll be below the
horizon and you won't be able to see it. So the line
about before חצות Chatzos and after חצות Chatzos mattering means that line
that שמואל Shmuel didn't know what it means, what it means is,
if the מולד Molad is before חצות, Chatzos, then it will
be visible that day. If the מולד Molad is after חצות, Chatzos,
it's not possible for the moon to be visible that day. Yes.
This is an approximate calculation depending on what time of year it
is. In the summer, yeah, they're actually you would actually get more
than six hours.
Yes, that's right because more than six hours of sunlight. That's a
very good point. Right. Okay, and it's also strange the assumption that
it only takes six hours to become visible because it's really again
astronomically I've seen that anywhere between
basically 18, some say maybe 15 and a half hours, but it
definitely takes a lot more than six hours to move off the
plane to be visible. All right, let's go just try to read
another line of the גמרא.
Wait, you use the word plane. You're talking about...
yeah. No, no, no. When I say moving off the plane, I
mean that the moon and the sun and the earth are in
line. Okay.
That's the plane. Is that what the מולד Molad is?
The מולד Molad is when it starts to move away from that
line.
Is that conjunction?
Conjunction.
Yes. Thank you. I was not using a technical term. Yes, in
conjunction they're exactly in line. The מולד Molad is when it moves
off that conjunction. Okay. Okay, so let's just read one more line.
אמר רב זירא אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav Zeira Amar Rav Nachman:
כד שעי מכסי סיהרא. Kaf daled sha'ei machasei sihara. Okay, so this
is the idea, it's covered for 24 hours. Now, לדידן שית מעתיקא
ותמני סרי מחדתא, Ledidan shis meetika v'samni srei mechadata, for us in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, six of the old month's moon can't be
seen and 18 of the new month's is hidden. לדידהו שית מחדתא
ותמני סרי מעתיקא, Ledidehu shis mechadata v'samni srei meetika, for them
in בבל, Bavel. six hours of the new moon can't be
seen and 18 hours of the old month moon can't be seen.
למאי נפקא מינה, Lemai nafka mina, what difference does it make? אמר
רב אשי לאכחושי סהדי, Amar Rav Ashi l'ach'chushi sahadi, in order to
contradict the witnesses. Okay, now this is the idea of 24 hours,
but this line is extremely difficult because for the reason I told
you, that in practice, the moon can't be seen 18 hours of
the old and 18 hours of the new. The nine degrees near
the sun is not visible in either direction. The other thing that
with the six and 18. The other thing that makes it difficult
is why does ארץ ישראל versus בבל Bavel, matter? And why would
it be such a radical shift? You're seeing the same moon in
בבל. Bavel But besides which, ארץ ישראל and בבל, Bavel there's less...
okay, you know, they're just seeing the exact same astronomical events like
an hour later, right? Just because בבל Bavel is a little bit
to the east, what difference does it make about how long the
moon is hidden from the sun or not? So this line is
extremely difficult to explain, I'm not really going to try. I will
give you one attempt, okay, we're really over time, but I'll just
give you one attempt to explain this, which is the following. Look
here back at what we've drawn here.
This is assuming that really, again, which is not true, but in
principle what as if, we'll assume that the גמרא thinks that the
moon is visible once it is six hours removed from the conjunction,
like we've been saying. Okay, so in that case, in this scenario,
okay, let's just follow this scenario for a moment,
okay, it's removed from the conjunction, the מולד Molad is after חצות.
Chatzos. Okay, in that case, is it going to be visible here?
No, because it'll only begin to be visible after sunset. Okay, so
it's hidden for these six hours, hidden, hidden, hidden, hidden, hidden for
these 12 hours, and only becomes visible after sunrise. So in this
case, the new moon is hidden for 18 hours, right, 18 hours
the new moon can't be seen. Okay, the old moon, again, this
is assuming six hours is the actual period that it can't be
seen, the old moon was invisible for the previous six hours because
it was too close to the sun. So in this scenario, assuming
you only need a six-hour gap, it's six hours of the old
wasn't seen and 18 hours of the new. Okay, which is exactly
the reality assuming, A, you only need a six-hour gap, and B,
that the מולד Molad was exactly after חצות. Chatzos. Okay, now consider
the opposite case. The מולד Molad was exactly before חצות. Chatzos. If
the מולד Molad was exactly before חצות, Chatzos, it's visible right at
sunset, right? So the only time that it's hidden in this scenario
is only six hours of the new because it was visible right
at sunset. When was the last time the old one was visible?
Okay, so back here, in theory it was visible back here, but
then it was below the horizon, right? So the only real time
the last one was visible was way back here, 18 hours ago.
So in this case, you the old one was hidden for 18
hours and the new one was hidden for six hours. So do
you see, the little shift of before and after חצות. Chatzos. If
it was before חצות, Chatzos, the new... New one is hidden for
6 and the old one for 18, if it's after חצות, chatzos,
the new one is hidden for 18 and the old one for
6. So some want to say that's the difference it says between
בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל because בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל, the
shift of one hour from בבל to ארץ ישראל would shift the
scenario of the מולד molad after חצות chatzos to before חצות. chatzos.
And it's actually describing right those two cases. Now, okay, so I
don't know if you got that or you got just the gist,
but the basic point is that's a brilliant explanation. The only thing
that it has to assume is the what the גמרא we saw
already assumed, which is the moon is visible once it is six
hours removed from the conjunction, which actually isn't the case, but maybe
we could just say, I don't know, for some type of hypothetical,
if you assume it's visible after six hours from the conjunction, then
this issue of six and 18 from the old and the new
is all dependent on whether it was right before חצות chatzos or
right after חצות, chatzos, and that could be the difference of how
it would shift when you would move from בבל to ארץ ישראל,
that one-hour difference in time zone essentially would lead to that difference
of before and after חצות. chatzos. Okay, I hope you got some
of that.